<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Of all blasing starrs in generall, as well supernaturall as naturall, to what countrie or people so euer they appeare in the world vniuersall. The iudgement of the right reuerend Frederike Nause, Bishop of Vienna. Written and dedicated to the most high and puissaunt Emperour Ferdinand. Translated out of Latine into English, by Abraham Fleming</title>
            <title>Super huis anni post Christum natum M.D.XXXI. &amp; quolibet alio cometa exploratio. English</title>
            <author>Nausea, Friedrich, d. 1552.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 92KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B14918</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848365</idno>
  <idno type="VID">176506</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248552690</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 18413</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S113126</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99848365e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B14918)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176506)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 325:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Of all blasing starrs in generall, as well supernaturall as naturall, to what countrie or people so euer they appeare in the world vniuersall. The iudgement of the right reuerend Frederike Nause, Bishop of Vienna. Written and dedicated to the most high and puissaunt Emperour Ferdinand. Translated out of Latine into English, by Abraham Fleming</title>
                  <title>Super huis anni post Christum natum M.D.XXXI. &amp; quolibet alio cometa exploratio. English</title>
                  <author>Nausea, Friedrich, d. 1552.</author>
                  <author>Fleming, Abraham, 1552?-1607.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[80] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By H. Middleton?] for Thomas Woodcocke,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1577.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Super huis anni post Christum natum M.D.XXXI. &amp; quolibet alio cometa exploratio.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Of blasing starres. A doctrine generall.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Comets --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:176506:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176506:1"/>
            <p>Of all blasing starrs in generall, as well superna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall <hi>as naturall, to what countrie</hi> or people so euer they appeare in the world vniuersall.</p>
            <p>¶ The iudgement of the right re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend Frederike Nause, Bishop of Vienna.</p>
            <p>♣ Written and dedicated to the most high and puissaunt Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour Ferdinand.</p>
            <p>¶ Translated out of Latine into English, by <hi>Abraham Fleming.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for Thomas <hi>Woodcocke.</hi> 1577.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:176506:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176506:2"/>
            <head>To the Right worshipfull, and my singular good Patrone, Sir Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Cordell Knight, Maister of her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties Rolles, increase and continuance of health, wealth, and worship.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Emembrance of vndeserued fauour, (Right worshipfull) is a present spurre vnto me to continue deserued dutie: in consideration whereof, not knowing otherwise to seale an assurance of my thankful seruice, I haue (after my maner) employed my pen in translating a pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet, though breefe and compendious, yet pithie and profitable: whiche with wonted will I dedicate to your worship, in hope of accustomed courteous accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. Prudent and learned was he, by whome it was compiled: puissaunt and mightie, to whom it was presented: pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumptuous and vnskilfull, by whome it is translated: politike &amp; graue, to whom it is exhibited. The first was a Bishop of great reuerence, the second an Emperour
<pb facs="tcp:176506:3"/> of speciall renowne, the thirde an abiect of no reputation, &amp; the fourth a Knight of good worship and countenaunce. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whose sacred handes though this my trauell deserue not interteinment, in res<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of mine owne person being the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter: yet the name of the Preacher by whome it was written, and the same of the Gouernour to whome it was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, shall bring to my labour (I trust) suche countenaunce, as it shall of your worship be fauourably receiued, and of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery indifferent reader religiously reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced. The most mightie God and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour of all thinges, the euerlasting King who hath power ouer life &amp; death, and in whose treasurie are reposed all good graces for the comfort and benefit of his elect, inrich your worship with all maner blessings both corporal and men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, that when the dayes of your pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage are expired, you and yours may be receiued into Abrahams bosom, the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie harborough for all Gods chosen chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your worships by dutie bound, <hi>Abraham Fleming.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:176506:3"/>
            <head>To the Christian reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His generall doctrine (Christian reader) published vpon a speciall cause, namely, the appearing of a blasing starre at Mentz in Germanie 1531. when I had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>used &amp; pondered according to the mesure of mine vnderstanding and knowledge, I thought needful for the time to translate, and to commit to the present viewe of the world. Wherein, as there is nothing preiudicially spoken, which might kindle occasion of displeasure: so is nothing therein taught and discouered, but hath his groundworke of truth and veritie, (coniectures excepted, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, for their vncerteintie and falliblenesse, are accordingly to be considered,) and therefore the more notable. Farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine to vse Abraham Fleming.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:176506:4"/>
            <head>The summe or contents of this whole booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>WHy and wherevpon blasing starres haue their name. Chapter. 1.</item>
               <item>That blasing starres are sundry and diuers. Chapter. 2</item>
               <item>In what part of Heauen blasing starres appeare most commonly, Chapter. 3</item>
               <item>At what time of the yere blasing starres appeare, and how long they continue. Chapter. 4</item>
               <item>Whereof blasing starres be ingendered, (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the iudgement of Diuines) and what they are indeede. Chapter. 5</item>
               <item>Whereof blasing starres ingender, (according to the rules of Philosophers, and the canons of Astronomers,) and what they are indeed. Chapter. 6</item>
               <item>Whether the starre which conducted the wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, to the place where Christe was borne, were the blasing starre wherof the Emperour Augustus did speake, calling it by the name of a starre. Chapter. 7</item>
               <item>Whether blasing starres preport and foreshewe some straunge and wonderfull thing to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe. Chapter. 8</item>
               <item>The good and euill whiche blasing starres doe prognosticate and betoken. Chapter. 9</item>
               <item>The mischiefes which blasing starres forewarne to insue. Chapter. 10</item>
               <item>Sundrie examples and testimonies declaring the diuers and manifolde mischiefes which haue followed the appearing of blasing starres. Chapter. 11</item>
               <item>Whether blasing starres do not as well betoken good, as yll. Chapter. 12</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:176506:4"/>
               <item>To what countries, and to what persons blasing starres doe principally betoken yll. Chapter. 13</item>
               <item>Howe and what way blasing starres are fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warnings of somewhat to come, and of force so to doe. Chapter. 14</item>
               <item>Why blasing starres doe specially betoken yll to Peeres, Potentates, Rulers of realmes and Common wealthes. Chapter. 15</item>
               <item>Of a certeine blasing starre, which appeared in the yeare of our Lorde. 1531. the 19. of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember, at Mentz a citie in Germanie, and was sensibly seene likewise in other places. Chapter. 16</item>
               <item>Whether such euilles as blasing starres beto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, may by any meanes, either be preuented or auoyded. Chapter. 17</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:176506:5"/>
            <head>A Prognostication of bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing starres, after the opinion of the Poet Pontanus, and thus metrically Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>OF whisking windes, with blustering blasts which blowe</l>
               <l>Of bloudie broyles, by force in fatall fight:</l>
               <l>Of peoples pompe, the pittious ouerthrowe:</l>
               <l>Of Potentates the death (ah hellish spight:)</l>
               <l>The blasing starres aloft like lampes of light</l>
               <l>In th'East or West of azure coloured skies,</l>
               <l>Fore warnings are and signes when they arrise.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If still they stand, and offer not to chaunge</l>
               <l>The place, where first in sight they cast their beames,</l>
               <l>Then shall insue much mischiefe rare and straunge:</l>
               <l>As gaping woundes, yspowting bloudie streames,</l>
               <l>In foughten fielde, twixt nigh adioyning realmes.</l>
               <l>Such ciuil stormes shall ouerrunne the land,</l>
               <l>That some shall bath in kinreds bloud their hand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And if they take their course vnto the East,</l>
               <l>A signe it is that forreigne foes with force</l>
               <l>Prepare apace, to spoyle both most and least:</l>
               <l>With edge of sworde sweete life (ah) to diuorce</l>
               <l>From panting heart, saunce spirite of remorse.</l>
               <l>Thus East or West in sight, they haue their dome,</l>
               <l>And signes they are of things in time to come.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ab. Fleming.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:176506:5"/>
            <head>Why, and whereupon Blasing Starres haue their names. Chapter. 1.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orsomuche as a man furnished with all kind of knowledge and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, should so searche after y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> vnderstanding of loftie and high mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, that he haue not meaner things in contempt and disdaine, by whose be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit (as experience teacheth) the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter are atteined, because they minister certeine helpes and aydes to aspire and reache vnto them: wherevpon it follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth, that lesser thinges are not to bée neglected, without the which there is no passage to the greater, nor any possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie to pearce to the perfect proofe of them, excepte by the forerunning of these, preparation be made for vs to as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cende &amp; climbe vp to the hidden know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb facs="tcp:176506:6"/> of the other: therefore, lest this our labour lent and laide out for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon vtilitie and profite, should be sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the battering blowes of furious enuie, and lest such as desire perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in profession, and certeintie in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuering doctrine, should complaine, that we sell shadowes for substaunces, phantasies for verities, and imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for demonstrations, we will say somewhat, in the entraunce of this woorke, touching the name of a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mete or Blasing starre, and so passe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly to our purpose.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A Blasing star is named after the forme &amp; figure whiche it beareth.</note>The starre which the Grecians call <hi>Cometes,</hi> the Latines <hi>Stella crinita,</hi> we Englishmen a Blasing starre, hath his denomination, (as well by the asserti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the one, as the other) from the forme and figure which it beareth, at such time as it appeareth in the Aire: bycause this kinde of starre séemeth (in our opinion and iudgement) to shoote our long strakes of fire in the element, or bright and lightsome sparckles con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in length, like vnto haire, which the <hi>Graecians</hi> call <hi>Coma,</hi> &amp; thereupon
<pb facs="tcp:176506:6"/>
               <hi>Cometa,</hi> &amp; the Latines <hi>Crinis,</hi> whereof it is named <hi>Stella crinita:</hi> so that the resemblaunce or representation which this starre giueth, is the occasion that it is called a Comet or Blasing starre. As <hi>Augustus Caesar</hi> called that starre which appeared at such time as he published pageants of pleasure, and shewes of tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, by the name of a Comete: and which <hi>Suetonius Tranquillus</hi> called <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus crinitum,</hi> and diuers others haue semblably termed.</p>
            <p>Neyther was the imposition of this name absurde, or against reason: for whosoeuer shall narrowly behold these kinde of starres, hée shall perceiue, (though not most perfectly, yet not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie darkely) howe it spitteth out long &amp; slender lines of sparckling fire this way and that way: in so muche as a man would thinke and suppose the same not vnlike vnto scattered haire,<note place="margin">The likenes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of Blasing starres, as som<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>times they appeare.</note> to a broome or a rodde of Byrche, to the taile of a Pecocke, to the bearde of a man, &amp;c. as we are taught by demonstration.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:176506:7"/>
            <head>That Blasing starres are sundrie and diuerse. Chap. 2.</head>
            <p>BLasing starres are not onely verie manie in number, but also diuerse in appearance. The sect of the Stoikes saide, that they are beyonde two &amp; thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, of whose sundrie names and seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall effectes <hi>Abienus</hi> (not vnwisely) hath written.</p>
            <p>Concerning their number &amp; names we are not curious, wherefore we will come to their colours and likenesses, wherein there is not a vniformitie and generall agréement, but a difference. For some Blasing starres séeme bloud red,<note place="margin">Blasing starres differ in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour.</note> horrible to beholde, and as it were crisped and curled in the crowne, or vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per parte tending towardes the skies, wherevppon they are commonly called Cometes: of which the Poet hath this saying.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Like as in moyst and dewishe night,</l>
               <l>When Comets red as blood</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:176506:7"/>
               <l>Appeare aloft: a spectacle</l>
               <l>and signe of little good.</l>
            </q>
            <p>This figure haue they,<note place="margin">Blasing starres varie in figure</note> when they are thicke on the one side, and stretched out in length on the other side.</p>
            <p>Some Blasing starres there bée, which haue a traine hanging downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde at their lower parte, in the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of a long bearde, or the maine of a horse: which happeneth by reason of the thinne matter and substance which is in the other partes, which kinde of starres are called <hi>Pogonii.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Othersome there are, which appeare in the likenesse of a Speare or Iauelin, and they are called <hi>Acontii:</hi> of suche a one (as testifieth <hi>Plinie</hi>) did <hi>Tiberius Caesar</hi> in his fift Consulship, penne pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing and excellent Poemes, or verses of notable inuention and singular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyaunce.</p>
            <p>Other some there are, shorter some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what then y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> former, &amp; they be sharpe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the top like a sword, whereupon they are called <hi>Piphii,</hi> resembling in colour Golde after a sorte, but yet so
<pb facs="tcp:176506:8"/> notwithstanding, that of all other they are moste pale, wanting beames, bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, or strakes, hauing neuerthelesse a certeine brightnesse in them, like the glittering of a sworde.</p>
            <p>Other some there are which are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Phitites,</hi> in forme and fashion like a tunne, hauing in the hollowe parte of it the shewe of a smoakie and smoothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring flame, much like vnto the blacke Smithes forge, or vessels daubed and sméered with pitche sett on fire, which cast a darke &amp; mistie light, which men haue sometimes vsed for the preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and freshe kéeping of their drinke.</p>
            <p>There are besides them that wée haue reckoned, Comets called <hi>Ceratii,</hi> because they appeare to our sight in the similitude and likenesse of a horne: such a one was séene when the Grecians in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camped at <hi>Salamis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Othersome also are there, which be called <hi>Lampades,</hi> because they cast a shewe of a burning torche, or flaming lampe, of which sort sundrie haue béene séene, and that not verie seldome.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, some there are which
<pb facs="tcp:176506:8"/> be called <hi>Hippei,</hi> because they séeme to haue about them, as it were, a horse maine, going round about them in cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle wise, with straunge mouing and swiftnesse.</p>
            <p>To be short,<note place="margin">A blasing starre repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senting (as it were in a glasse) the image of God</note> some blasing starres are séene in the Aire, glistering with strakes and streames like bright siluer, that it passeth the abilitie of mans eye to looke and beholde them, wherein (as in a cléere glasse) God is represented in the likenesse and shape of a man: and such a one (as some doe holde opinion) was that which appeared to the wise men in the East, and conducted them to the place where Christe was borne: concerning the appearing wherof, thus said they to the <hi>Hierosolomites: For we haue seene his starre in the East, and are come to do him worship.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But touching this, we purpose (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture) to say somwhat in the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vp of this worke. We knowe, that besides these which we haue rehearsed, there be many more formes &amp; figures of Cometes or Blasing starres, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more sortes, of which particularly
<pb facs="tcp:176506:9"/> to discourse is not our meaning or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, nor yet a matter of such weight &amp; importance, that it should require pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent &amp; perfecte handling: we will passe therefore to that which is more neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>In what parte of heauen Blasing starres appeare moste commonly. Chap. 3.</head>
            <p>THey that haue written things nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and profitable of Astrologie, and haue discouered things concerning the influencies &amp; gouernements of starres, in such sort &amp; order that the knowledge issuing from their traueyles offereth fruite not deseruing repentaunce, they (I saye) haue affirmed,<note place="margin">In what parte of heauen Blasing starres are seene.</note> that Blasing starres neuer appeare in the West part of heauen: but eyther vnder the North, in some one parte or other, but vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine: howbeit most commonly in that bright and cleare parte, which is called the milkie circle: or else (which is seel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb facs="tcp:176506:9"/> séene come to passe) they appeare in the South pole, but yet without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny blase, in the seasons of Winter es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially. Yet is it recorded, that a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met appeared to the Aethiopians, and to the Aegyptians, and that the King of those people gaue that Blasing starre a name, calling it <hi>Typon,</hi> because it had in it a double resemblance, namely of a round ball, and of a fire, in so much that, according to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> iudgement of sense, it might not so aptly be called a Comet or Blasing starre, as a fierie or flame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ball, or a round compassed and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning knott.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>At what time of the yere Blasing starres appeare, and howe long they continue. Chap. 4.</head>
            <p>ALthough <hi>Damascene</hi> (an author in my iudgement worthie reuerence) is of opinion that a Blasing starre is a starre newly made and created for the time present, which vanisheth out of
<pb facs="tcp:176506:10"/> sight, and ceasseth to appeare, when the thing whereof it is a signification is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complished and come to passe: yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding, experience (whome wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters name, the maistresse of manie my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries) infourmeth and teacheth vs, that a Blasing starre may appeare at any season of the yeare: but more often in Summer: and then specially, when the starre called <hi>Canicula</hi> ariseth and ruleth the weather &amp; time of the yeare, according to the proportion of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence:<note place="margin">The continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce of Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing starres in their appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring.</note> and that they continue seuen dayes at the least, and not aboue foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>score at the moste, the authoritie of <hi>Plinie</hi> giuing countenaunce to this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
            <p>Howbeeit, this assertion, together with the testimonie of <hi>Plinie,</hi> may be improued by examples: for (as it is vniuersally knowen) a Comete, which appeared before the ouerthrowe of Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem, was séene blasing in the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to the wonderfull astonishment of the people, by the space of a whole yeare: as <hi>Eusebius</hi> and <hi>Iosephus</hi> veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176506:10"/>
            <p>But we must note, that this Comet, &amp; the appearaunce of the same, which was full of horrour, is not to be ascri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed vnto Nature, but to be attributed immediately vnto God, the father and founder of Nature: although the secte of the Pythagoristes thought, that all Blasing starres were to bee referred vnto Nature, who hath prouided that their appearing should bee at certeine definite and appointed times of the yeare.</p>
            <p>Touching these Blasing starres al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, of the same sect there were some,<note place="margin">The opinion of the Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goristes tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching Blasing starres.</note> who supposed that they were perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all starres, and not temporall, and that they had an ordinarie course to runne, as other starres haue their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution and circular motion, and that their appearing procéeded from none other cause, then when they were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saken and lefte of the Sunne, whose brightnesse and néerenesse is the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion (as they thinke) that Blasing star<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res do not appeare.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:176506:11"/>
            <head>Whereof Blasing starres be ingendered (according to the iudgement of Diuines) and what they are in deede. Chap. 5.</head>
            <p>THE religious Diuines like verie well of this plausible and true opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that Blasing starres come of no other cause, then from the counsell and prouidence of God: that there is no matter of their generation as Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers imagine, but that God maketh them immediate messengers and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters of his will, according to the time and place, as it best pleaseth his high &amp; eternall maiestie: that by them hée might giue vs aduertisements of after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clappes, to prepare our selues onward to méete his fatherly mercie, or to suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the bytternesse of his sharpe iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: whereuppon they inferre this consequent, that Blasing starres are supernaturall, and méere worlds won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
            <p>To whose sentence I agrée, &amp; moste
<pb facs="tcp:176506:11"/> willingly assent, being thereto moued by arguments of forceable persuasion, and in number infinite. Principally, because it is a Christians dutie to as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe more to Gods prouidence, then to the force of Nature, whome God hath not onely created, but also doth dispose and gouerne. Yet for all that,<note place="margin">Some Blasing starres natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall.</note> I may not vtterly denie, that they are natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, for so much as I am not (or at least ought not to be) ignorant, that Nature causeth Blasing starres, howbeit so, that God is the originall and principall worker of such wonders, and that their groundes and causes are naturall, and not so secreat and doubtfull, but that other while the capacitie and reason of man may conceiue and compasse them. And yet contrariwise, I stande not in deniall, that those Blasing starres are supernaturall, which the most mightie Monarche of the heauens, Creator of all creatures, and Maker of all starres &amp; spirites, rayseth of nothing to some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, vppon a soudeine, in a moment and pricke of time, to the admiration of all men, and to the reuealing of his
<pb facs="tcp:176506:12"/> omnipotencie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">All things are possible to God.</note>Expedient and necessarie it is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue, that with God all things are in abilitie, and that whatsoeuer is done eyther by daye or by night, naturally, or supernaturally, it commeth to passe by his appointment, and that it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth him otherwhiles to create some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of something, and otherwhiles againe something of nothing: to that which neuer had matter, can he giue fashion and figure: and beautifie that with forme and comelinesse, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer had foundation or being. It con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisteth in his might to moysten y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> earth with shoures distilling from the cleare skies, without the meanes of lowring &amp; dropping cloudes. He can worke both wayes, to whome nothing is impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, nowe gathering the cloudes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in an heape, from the vttermost corners and coastes of the worlde, now turning lightening into raine, now co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering the heauens with cloudes, and preparing raine for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> land: For, <hi>Great is the Lorde, mightie is his power, and of his wisedome there is no number or
<pb facs="tcp:176506:12"/> end:</hi> and therefore I am easily drawne to beléeue, that Blasing starres may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare immediately from God, and be supernatural, when it pleaseth God vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon some singular cause to giue them beginning, matter, and substaunce of nothing.</p>
            <p>Such a Blasing starre (no doubte) was that Piller of the cloude,<note place="margin">The piller of the cloude, &amp; the piller of fire were Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing starres supernaturall.</note> whereby the Lorde in olde time moste miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lously went before the Israelites his people out of the Aegyptian soile, into the lande of promise in the day time: and that Piller of fire whiche neuer lefte the face of Gods chosen people in the night.</p>
            <p>Not vnlike to this, was that Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing starre (as I suppose) which threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning destruction to Hierusalem,<note place="margin">The Blasing starre which appeared in Hierusalem was superna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall.</note> was of no lesse continuaunce then terrour, induring the space of a whole yeare, which is not proper to naturall Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing starres.</p>
            <p>To conclude, as well Diuines, as Philosophers &amp; Astronomers, affirme thus muche in this case, that alwayes
<pb facs="tcp:176506:13"/> in a maner) Blasing starres spring of causes naturall, albeit the Lord God is the principall author and worker of them, as in the Chapter following it is euident.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>Whereof Blasing starres ingender, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the rules of Philosophers, and the Canons of Astrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, and what they are in deede. Chap. 6.</head>
            <p>COncerning Blasing starres, I finde some disagréement betwéene Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sophers and Astronomers. <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> and <hi>Democritus</hi> saide, that a Blasing starre was nothing else, but a certeine bright shining in the element, procured by the coniunction of two starres: to the which opinion I my selfe of late did somewhat incline and leane.</p>
            <p>Othersome also there were, whiche supposed a Blasing starre to bee but a certeine dimme and darke light com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passed, and (as it were) closed vp in a
<pb facs="tcp:176506:13"/> cloud. Other some saide, that it was a cloude purged and clarified from all earthly matter and grossenesse, whiche receiuing light from the other starres, casteth abroade cleare strakes of bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, small and slender like haire or fine wrought flaxe.</p>
            <p>Othersome againe, thought a Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing starre to be but a certeine cloude, kindled and set on fire with a hotte fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming clearenesse,<note place="margin">Aristotle his opinion of Blasing starrs, and their ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration.</note> whose opinion <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stotle</hi> séemeth to haue fauoured, who supposed that a Blasing starre did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist of a drie vapour, which being dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen vpwarde into the highest Aire, is there set on fire: and that this Blasing starre taketh substance of earthly exha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, verie hott, drie, fatt, and clam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, which being carried into the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per region of the Aire, is there kindled and burneth. To whome all Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sophers (in a manner) of this our age, haue subscribed, &amp; some Astronomers also, who with <hi>Aristotle</hi> think no lesse, then a Blasing starre to bee but an earthly vapour, somewhat thicke, fast, &amp; fatt in substaunce, like oyle or birde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime,
<pb facs="tcp:176506:14"/> which being drawne vpwarde, nigh to the Sphere of the firie element, and touching the hollownesse of the orbe or circle, is there by heat rarified, made thinne and sett in a flame. So that by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> consent &amp; mutuall agréement of these two sects, (although some do va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie) it is concluded, that a Blasing starr is ingendred &amp; made of aire set on fire, by reason of the néerenesse of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> element of fire, that aire conteining in it y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter &amp; stuffe of a Blasing starre, &amp; that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> aire next adioyning, &amp; being by the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of fire, is called a Blasing starre, &amp; is no lesse in déede then it is named: which representeth the colour of fire to our eyes, because the drie vapour in it is kindeled, burneth, &amp; lasteth with the light of the flame, which is moued to &amp; fro by the vnder aire, where vapours of like nature, qualitie &amp; substaunce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rising, giue continuance &amp; length there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, whereby it purchaseth the name, after which it is vsually called.</p>
            <p>Vppon this agrée our late Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, in a manner all, counting the doctrine of <hi>Aristotle</hi> woorthie credite &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:176506:14"/> subscription: although as well the sect Stoicall varie therefro,<note place="margin">The opinion of the Stoiks touching Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing starres.</note> affirminge Blasing starres to bee but ordinarie starres, not differing from other star<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res which appeare in the aire, &amp; to bée aboue thirtie and two in number: as also they, which holde this for a veritie, Blasing starres to bee perpetuall star<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, and to kéepe a limitted course or compasse, but neuer to blase and gli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster in the Aire, saue when they are lefte and forsaken of the Sunne, whose clearenesse dimmeth and dampeth vpp their brightnesse, that it can neyther appeare nor be perceiued: and they in like sort, which leane to this opinion, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Blasing starres, be starres, hauing their certeine appointed times of apperance.</p>
            <p>Now, as I dissent not from the first, those I meane, whose opinion draweth néerest to reason and trueth: so I varie not altogether from them, who holde o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion that a Blasing starre may be su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall, and also naturall, &amp; that the same taketh generation of a fatt hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, and of fierie force, whereby it is dissolued, and at the length consumeth.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176506:15"/>
            <p>Whereuppon this consequent is to be inferred, that we cannot call a Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing starre, properly a starre: but cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrestically, as we may so terme them, I meane, vsing in our phrase of speach a certeine abuse: although <hi>Augustus Caesar</hi> (whereof we haue giuen a caue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at in the beginning of this our treatise) called that Blasing starre which appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at such time as he published his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geantes of triumph, by the name of a starre: and which vsurped name also <hi>Suetonius</hi> applieth to the selfe same thing: they bothe adding vnto it this worde <hi>Crinitus,</hi> which we also, with no lesse abuse then they, call Blasing.</p>
            <p>This Blasing starre aforesaid, which appeared in the time of <hi>Augustus Caesar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">An erronious opinion mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iked and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued.</note> and shined so gloriously, some ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, and suppose, to be the selfe same starre which directed the wisemen to the place where Christe was borne. But I cannot allowe of this opinion, &amp; why I do so much mislike thereof, the reasons in the next Chapter following, do declare. In the meane season, I would not wade in wonders aboue
<pb facs="tcp:176506:15"/> my capacitie, least I wander in wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernesses of doubts, but I desire rather to be wise with sobernesse.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>Whether the starre which conducted the wise men to the place where Christ was borne, were the Blasing starre, whereof the Emperour Augustus did speake, calling it by the name of a starre. Chap. 7.</head>
            <p>CHristian duetie admonisheth mée, in fewe wordes to make mention what maner of miraculous &amp; straunge starre that was, which after a rare and wonderfull fashion, lead the wise men vnto Christe beeing in his infancie: which some men, verie rashly, &amp; with want of aduisement, coniecture to be the Blasing starre, which appeared and cast a great light at the same time that <hi>Augustus Caesar</hi> made shewes of greate pompe and solemnitie: whose arising was in the North parte of heauen, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the eleuenth houre of the day, and
<pb facs="tcp:176506:16"/> continued (as <hi>Plinie</hi> plainely testifieth) seuen dayes space full and complete.</p>
            <p>Of which thing, although <hi>Picus Mirandula</hi> hath both godly and grauely discoursed, yet thinke I, that it is my duetie, compendiously to reason, what in this point may be mainteined, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hurt or preiudice: and so much the rather, because I woulde not séeme in this matter, to fauour the Astrologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, for somuch as they swarue as farr from trueth, as the worlde is wide, &amp; the heauen is high.</p>
            <p>Concerning the starre, therefore, which appeared at Christ his natiuitie, the Euangelist, whose euidence is tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the touchstone of trueth, wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in this wise.<note place="margin">For we haue seene his starr in the East.</note>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: Among all which wordes of this clause, penned by the finger of the Euangelist, the Latine interpreter turneth this woorde <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Stellam,</hi> learnedly (no doubte) &amp; truely. The Euangelist yet againe sayth thus: <hi>And, Beholde, the starre which they sawe in the East, went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, vntill by approching, it
<pb facs="tcp:176506:16"/> stoode ouer the place, where the babe was.</hi> By these testimonies, it is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and manifest, that neyther <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, nor <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, signifie a Blasing starre. Whereby the errours of <hi>Phlegon</hi> and <hi>Harpocrates</hi> are conuinced, who also déemed that the starre which shewed &amp; shined in the East, and was the wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens direction to <hi>Iudea,</hi> was the selfe same Blasing starre, which in the time of <hi>Augustus Caesar</hi> (as is aforesaide) so gloriously glistered: when it is as eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent as the Sunne shine at noone day,<note place="margin">They appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie regions, &amp; at sundrie times of great distance, ergo they were dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent starres.</note> howe that Blasing starre appeared ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie yeres before the natiuitie of Christ, and arose in the North parte of heauen: whereas the starre which was the wise mens guid into <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> apeared in the East. Furthermore, what man would so soone be allured to beléeue, that a Blasing starre woulde be thought of the wisemen, a thing of such certeine &amp; infallible prognostication, that the ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing &amp; procéeding thereof should embol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den them to cōmence such tedious ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys, &amp; to attempt so many wearie la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labours, when they might bee of this
<pb facs="tcp:176506:17"/> opinion and iudgement as well, that the Blasing starre gaue foreknowledge of something else, besides the natiuitie and byrth of the King of the Iewes.</p>
            <p>Wherefore it is more credible, that those wise men followed y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> starre which then appeared, eyther vpon persuasion of the booke which <hi>Seth</hi> compiled, or els by the motion of <hi>Balaams</hi> prophesie: for that they were of the kinred and affini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of him, as some helde opinion: or else by the ministerie of Angels, or by heauenly inspiration, or else by admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition and warning giuen in sléepe, which might (why not?) giue them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding as well of this, as it gaue them knowledge afterwards to auoyd the presence of <hi>Herod,</hi> and to returne another way into their countrie, and not the same, by which they came.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Iulianus the Apostata his opinion, as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to reason &amp; ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, refuted.</note>No man is able sufficiently to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the erronious opinion of <hi>Iulianus</hi> that irreligious reuolter, who affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth this starre, which he calleth by the name of <hi>Asaph,</hi> according to the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Aegyptians, of custome and wont, to appeare euery foure hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth
<pb facs="tcp:176506:17"/> yeares, &amp; that it betokeneth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things both meruellous and mortal. But tell mée thou false Prophet and peruerse Apostata, if thou wilt haue thine opinion carie away countenance of credit, How commeth it to passe, that those wise men neuer atteined to the vnderstanding of that starre, and the determinate arising of the same at a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite and appointed time, but that they then came to the intelligence thereof, when it was within the contemplation and viewe of their eyes? Howe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth it to passe, that the appearaunce thereof was so farre from horrour and mortalitie, that it gaue presignificatiō of ioy, that to them was borne the King of the Iewes? And if it be effectuall to worke wonders, &amp; to compasse strange and prodigious euentes, why then did it not euery foure hundreth yeares, by succession, season and degrées of time, prognosticate some semblable thing, like vnto that which was communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the knowledge of the wise men? Why did it not, after a thousande, fiue hundreth and thirtie yeares, or within
<pb facs="tcp:176506:18"/> the compasse &amp; reuolution of that time, bring forth a newe King to the world, or some other rare and wonderfull ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, to kindle in the hearts of men, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest admiration? Or else, if it suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red an Eclipse or depriuation, of that singular qualitie, and so became drie, barren, and vnfruitefull, why did it not appeare still, though weakened in working, but lost vtterly and for euer appearaunce in the heauens?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A conclusion of reasoning interlaced with a shorte and sharpe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehension.</note>Thou swaruest therefore and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derest farre and wide from the sincere trueth, and giuest a witnesse of thy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinacie to all people, and of thy foule impietie towardes God, in that thine own opiniō, which is méere erronious, séemeth vnto thée passing plausible: thou in the meane season derogating from Christian religion due reuerence, and struggling with tooth and nayle to make it contemptible. But all in vaine thou wrestlest with the waues, which in the ende will ouerwhelme thée in thy wilfulnesse. For, the trueth giueth in a contrarie verdict, against thée, with the which whosoeuer haue armed thēselues
<pb facs="tcp:176506:18"/> to enconter, their successe hath not béen prosperous, beecause they attempted combate with a mightier then themsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, and being ouermatched were car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried into captiuitie, and cast into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion. This starre therefore, which the wisemen sawe,<note place="margin">The authors iudgement in the winde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vp of this controuersie.</note> was no Comet or Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing starr, as diuerse haue dreamed, but some new starre, which of purpose was appointed to expresse the prouidence of the Almightie, as in the Gospel it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent: not being of the number &amp; host of them, where with God garnished the firmament in the vniuersall creation, but differing from all starrs, both fixed, wandering, &amp; blasing: which to be true, this testimonie affordeth authoritie: for that there be some which are of this iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement, and holde it for a veritie, That in this starre, as in a glasse, was inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the likenes of a child: into which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion they might (peraduenture) bee induced, by the words of the wisemen, saying: <hi>Behold we haue seene his starre in the East.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It could not choose then, but be a new starre, &amp; a starre importing a miracle:
<pb facs="tcp:176506:19"/> for so much, as neyther the selfe same, nor any like vnto it, euer appeared in the former ages, nor at any time shined in the skies, for the space of a thousand, fiue hundreth, and thirtie yeares, after the natiuitie of our comfortable Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our: being, I say, a starre by the grace of God created, for the execution of his message, whose pleasure being accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plished, it consumed, vanished, and was no longer obiect to the eyesight of men, being causall and temporall, not naturall and continuall.</p>
            <p>But of this discourse sufficient is said as well for the improuing of vnsauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie opinions, as also for the discoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the infallible trueth, requirea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in this present purpose. Now will I make a retrogradation, and returne to mine argumente concerning Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mets or Blasing stars, hauing thought my penne not vnfruitefully occupied in this last particular.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>Whether blasing starres preport and foreshewe some straunge and wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full thing to followe. Chap. 8.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:176506:19"/>
            <p>IT is called in controuersie, whether Cometes, commonly termed Blasing starres, preporte any prodigious thing and worldes wonder. Some in this behalfe, séeme to be resolued,<note place="margin">Blasing starrs are signes of some strange thing to come</note> and make their aunswer in this sorte: That as blasing starres are rare and seldome, so they signifie some thing y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is rare and straunge: vnto whiche opinion they cleaue, being therevnto drawen part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by daily experience, and partely al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so lead by the causes from the whiche they fett their originall.</p>
            <p>And, to say the plaine trueth, when haue Blasing stars cast their glimme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring beames, and lightened the aire with their glistering brightnesse, but something hath followed, contrarie to common course, and farre otherwise then by vsuall and accustomed order is receiued? Why then should not Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing starres as they are rare, so inferre and drawe with them rare effects? And why shoulde we otherwise thinke, then that by their generation also, some straunge thing is signified: seeing that other starrs shining in the firmament,
<pb facs="tcp:176506:20"/> are thought, not only to haue bene crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the seruice of men, but also for the distinguishing of times &amp; seasons, of dayes, houres, monethes and yéeres, and for other ends also, which are priuy only to Gods secret counsel? Specially, for that our Lord Iesus, iudged not the superstitious Pharisées (notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his sore denunciations of woes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them) altogether deseruing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehension:<note place="margin">The Phariseis and Sadduce is not altogether condemned for their due &amp; precise obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the weather.</note> nor vtterly blamed y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces, for their diligent obseruation of the weather, and marking the face of the firmament, giuing iudgement: that if the helpe of heauen were such &amp; suche, then semblable to be the succes of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons: as if it were couered with redd cloudes in the euening, that then men should be in epectation of the next day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es bright clearenes. Which ceremonie of theirs, purchased in processe of time, such credit and beléefe, that it grewe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a common and familiar prouerbe.</p>
            <q>
               <l>What man can say of certeintie?</l>
               <l>The euening this doth signifie.</l>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>The good and euil which Blasing starrs
<pb facs="tcp:176506:20"/> do prognosticate &amp; betoken. Cap. 9.</head>
            <p>AS it is receiued for an vndoubted trueth, that Comets carrie with thē a prognosticatiō of some strange won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: so on the other side, it hath bene pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cisely noted, &amp; by due obseruation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> they threten some imminent euill and mischiefe.<note place="margin">A blasing star is a token of great feare, &amp; a signe of hor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ror.</note> For which conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, a Blasing starre was called a signe of horror, or a token of great fear, by which name excellent men, authors (I meane) or writers of singular lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning &amp; iudgement haue termed it: not that the Blasing star is to be feared, as if it could doe harme vnto man: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the omnipotent God, &amp; guide of the heauenly hoaste, by the same, as by a burning beacon, giueth vs warnings and watch words of afterclappes &amp; pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment: and to assure vs, that he it is, and none besides him, that is vniuersal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be feared, not with a seruile, but with a filiall feare: consideringe that hée hath peremptorie power ouer the whole manne, bodie and soule, vppon whiche partes he consisteth: and is of
<pb facs="tcp:176506:21"/> abilitie to adiudge vs to temporall cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stisement for our amendment: or else to condemne vs to eternall destruction, as instruments of reprobation.</p>
            <p>But to returne to the prognostica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Cometes or Blasing starres, it is found by authoritie, that in the time of Charles the Emperour,<note place="margin">A Blasing starre in the time of Caro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Magnus.</note> surnamed, The great, a Blasing starre appeared, in the contemplation whereof the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour hauing his eyes earnestly bent, &amp; considering profoundly thereupon, at length he was rapt into a great asto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment, touching the signification of the same: and sending for a Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, named Egmard, conferred and reasoned to &amp; fro with him about this starre, saying in conclusion, that the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing thereof did threaten vnto him some miserable calamitie: which words the Philosopher hearing, to the intent that the Emperour shoulde not be more amased then néede required, rehearsed the saying of the Prophet in these wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des: <hi>A Signis coeli nolite metuere: <hi>Feare ye not the signes of Heauen, and let not the visions of the firmament strike ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour
<pb facs="tcp:176506:21"/> into your heartes.</hi>
               </hi> Which sentence the Emperour not misliking, gaue him thankes for that comfortable counsell, saying, that hee remembred the due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of a christian man to be this, namely to stand in feare of nothing, but only of him, who both created vs and also this starre. Which notable speache of so fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous an Emperour, giueth a sensible instruction, why a Blasing starre may be called a token of terrour, or a signe of horrible feare.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Plinie</hi> also (many yeares past) affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, a Comet to be a terrible starre,<note place="margin">A Blasing starre threate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> &amp; so inclined to destruction, that it deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to be called mortall: as in the ciuil commotion, which was in the time of <hi>Octauius</hi> his Consulshippe: and also in the warre betwéene <hi>Pompeius</hi> and <hi>Caesar,</hi> many probabilitis are to be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, or rather, many verities to be aduouched. To the wordes of whiche <hi>Plinie, Vergil</hi> (the prince of all Poets and <hi>Plinies</hi> predecessour) alludeth, in this wise.</p>
            <q>
               <l>More flashing flames of lightnings cleare,</l>
               <l>From clouds shine not beelowe:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:176506:22"/>
               <l>Nor blasing starrs, whose burning beames,</l>
               <l>Some fatall fall doth showe. &amp;c.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And the same Poet, in another place inserteth these wordes:
<q>
                  <l>Strange stars did shine from skies in darksom night</l>
                  <l>And flakes of fire did fil the ayre with light</l>
                  <l>A blasing star with siluered straks did shine,</l>
                  <l>And made mens harts for fear away to pine</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Whome the Poet <hi>Lucanus</hi> imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and setting before him, as a presi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, for the obseruation of order, vseth these tearmes and phrases of speach in his Poemes:
<q>
                  <l>Not blasing starr with glimmering strakes of light</l>
                  <l>And lengthned haires of color red &amp; white,</l>
                  <l>Which brings to men (as many make report)</l>
                  <l>Destruction dire in lamentable sorte.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Whereby it is to be gathered, that those kinde of writers were not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, that a Comet or Blasing starr, did moste commonly presignifie and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shew some imminent mischiefe, which in tract of time came to passe, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vppon grewe in vse to be called, A terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or fearefull starre.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The mischiefe whiche Blasing starres forewarne to insue. Cap. 10.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:176506:22"/>
            <p>FOrsomuch as it is declared alreadie, that Blasing starres alwayes signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie nothing else, then the approching of some pernicious and mischiefous thing likely after to insue: it remaineth, that this question be demanded, What ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of euills they be, whereof Blasing starres are premonstrations, and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tokens? Wherevnto I make this aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere, That as Blasing starres are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerse, so are their effectes &amp; euils which they signifie, not all one, but sundrie &amp; differing: and forsomuch as the varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or diuersitie of them is to be conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, therefore it is necessarie that the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects whiche followe such causes, be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly coniectured.</p>
            <p>Some holde opinion,<note place="margin">The obserua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vsed of some at the appearing of Blasing starres</note> that it is to be marked, whiche way Blasing starres shoot their light, because (say they) that part of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> earth séemeth to be thretened, towardes which the Comet casteth his beams thickest &amp; most directly. Againe, it is to be noted, from what starre they receiue their force, &amp; whence procéedeth their influence, what thinges they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semble, and represent in likenesse, and in what places they appeare.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176506:23"/>
            <p>Furthermore, to touche the effectes of Blasing starres,<note place="margin">The effectes which haue followed Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing starres, proued true by experience</note> experiences mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde and innumerable haue sealed this for a trueth, that sometimes they signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie barrennesse of the earth, sometimes the sicknesse of the plague &amp; pestilence, sometimes dearth, and scarsitie of vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuals, sometimes great windes &amp; tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pestes, sometimes extreme heate, som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times earthquakes, sometimes the flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing of waters beyond their boundes &amp; bankes, to the drowning and losse of the lande, sometimes seditions, insur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, cruell commotions, tumultes, &amp; battels, sometimes chaunge of Kings and Kingdomes, alterations of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealthes, and such slaughters as seldome are séene, with many mo ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities, infinite and innumerable: in so much that <hi>Lucanus</hi> the Poet thought it no matter of doubt, but of assured cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teintie, to call a Blasing starre, such a starre, as changed y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> state of Empires, &amp; wrought the alteration of principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities. His verses followe in this order.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Straunge starres were seene in darkesome nights,</l>
               <l>The heauen was on a flame:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:176506:23"/>
               <l>And flakes of fire like burning brands,</l>
               <l>Sore sightes in skies did frame.</l>
               <l>The fearefull starre which blaseth bright,</l>
               <l>And spreades his beames abrode,</l>
               <l>And changeth kingdomes in the world,</l>
               <l>In th'aire aboue abode.</l>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <head>Sundrie examples, and testimonies, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring the diuerse and manifolde mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes, which haue followed the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Blasing starres. Chap. 11.</head>
            <p>LEaste any man shoulde thinke this méere fabulous, &amp; a verie forgerie, because I haue sayed thus muche, and that vppon the opinion and authoritie of other writers, that diuerse Blasing starres presignifie, and giue a forewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of diuerse mischiefes &amp; euils like to come, it séemeth vnto mée an enterprise worth my labour, to set downe in a few wordes, and the selfe same conspireing with the true reportes of Histories, the assertion aboue mentioned, not to bee imaginarious or feigned. Wherein it shall not séeme a matter depending vpon necessitie, to runne thorough all
<pb facs="tcp:176506:24"/> particular example, and to make a vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersall repetition of testimonies from the worlds creation: (which passeth the capacitie of my wit to comprehend, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they excéede in multitude:) But it shall rather be sufficient, &amp; muche more profitable, out of many to gather a few, and such indéede, as authors most wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of credite haue sett downe in their workes and treatises.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A short enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>tion or rehearsall of mischiefes which follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon the ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pering of Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing starres.</note>And first of all to begin with the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blest writers, and best approued: who is ignorant, that after the appearaunce of a Comet in the time of <hi>Iulius Caesar,</hi> not only ciuil warres followed, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner most lamentable, but also the death &amp; murthering of <hi>Iulius Caesar</hi> his owne person, which was most miserable: who béeing sixe and fiftie yéeres of age, was assaulted and set vpon in a conspiracie, of thrée score Princes and more, among whom were <hi>C. Cassius, Marcus,</hi> and <hi>D. Brutus:</hi> and béeing gored through, and slasht with thrée and twentie woundes in the Court of <hi>Pompeius</hi> despitefully perished: whereof <hi>P. Virgilius, Luca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Plinie, Suetonius, Appianus, Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarchus,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:176506:24"/> and diuerse other writers of great authoritie are witnesses.</p>
            <p>What should I linger longe in the repetition of those straunge tempestes, of snowes, hailes, inundations of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and other like calamities, that followed the appearing of the same Blasing starre? Whiche <hi>F. Horatius</hi> doth not nakedly describe, but singular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly sette downe, with a kinde of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint.</p>
            <p>Who knoweth not, what an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakable desolation, and wonderfull ouerthrowe of <hi>Hierusalem</hi> Citie, follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed after the appearing of a certeine Blasing starre, whiche was séene in the aire, (<hi>Iosephus</hi> and <hi>Eusebius</hi> faithfully affirming no lesse,) by the space of a whole yeare, burning with flames of lamentable destruction?</p>
            <p>The selfe same miserable massacre and desolation followed shortely after this Blasing starre, whiche the Lorde himselfe, the Father of all mercie, and Iudge of all reuengement, did not only fortell many yeres, yer it came to passe: but also wept for very sorrow of heart,
<pb facs="tcp:176506:25"/> as he was prophesying to <hi>Hierusalem,</hi> her sharp visitation. For our Sauiour Christe (as the Euangelists testifie) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the Citie, wept ouer her, &amp; soun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as it were in her eares this sorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full sentence: <hi>If thou haddest knowne,</hi> (saith he) <hi>in that thy daye, those things which belonged vnto thy peace, and nowe are hidden from thine eyes &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A Blasing starre appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before the death of the Emperour Constantine.</note>Did not the death of that most godlie and religious Emperour <hi>Constantine,</hi> followe and insue the appearing of a Blasing starre, which was séene in the yeare of our Lord 304. being of an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accustomed bignesse, and of no lesse horrour to behold? And did not thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon likewise followe an excéeding dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous insurrection in the Empire, wherein, among many murthers and bloudsheds the Emperour <hi>Constantius</hi> was spoyled of his life, in the Castell of <hi>Helena,</hi> not farre from Spaine?</p>
            <p>In the yeare of our Lorde 444. a Blasing starre was séene, which as it gaue presignifications &amp; foretokens of afterclaps, so did there insue moste mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable slaughters and calamities, spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb facs="tcp:176506:25"/> in <hi>Fraunce:</hi> &amp; not long after <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> being assalted and beséeged of the Hunnes, was ransackt, spoyled, &amp; made euen in a maner with the ground: and y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> most Catholique Emperour <hi>Martian,</hi> was in a conspiracie of his owne sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, contrarie to the religious othe of allegiance, murthered and made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way at <hi>Constantinople.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After the appearing of a starre in the yeare of our Lorde, fiue hundred,<note place="margin">A meruellous inundation of waters with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther notable calamities fore warned by a Blasing starre.</note> foure score and foure, there followed such an inundation of waters, in euery place of the land, that it was auerred and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeued, a seconde deluge or vniuersall floude to haue béene prepared for the drowning of the whole worlde. After y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> insued in Italie, so hott a pestilence, that within the compasse of a litle time, many thousandes died in maner most lamentable. Not long after that <hi>Rome</hi> tasted of the whip: for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
               <hi>Lombards</hi> lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing séege against it, made hauocke ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of out of measure. Vppon the tayle of whiche sharpe punishment, there fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed a worsse: for the Sarracens rose vpp with stearne lookes and bending
<pb facs="tcp:176506:26"/> browes, compelling the third part (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most) of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> world which professed Chris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tianitie, to fall to Apostasie, and to take parte with them in their damnable sect of diuelish idolatrie, and detestable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlinesse.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A Blasing star appeared be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the death of Carolus Magnus.</note>In the yeare of our Lord eight hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and thirtéene, there was a Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing starre séene most straunge and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible, wherevpon insued y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> death of that most Christian Emperour <hi>Carolus Magnus.</hi> The Saracens assalted <hi>Italie</hi> and with violence of sworde and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like engine ouercame and preuailed: not without y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ruine of many a beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful building, &amp; sheding of much bloud.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Bloudie bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telles whiche followed after the appearing of a Blasing starre.</note>In the yeare of our Lord a thousand two hundred foure score &amp; foure, there appeared a Blasing starre, which did portend a manifest shewe of much mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe and miserie: for in the yeare of our Lorde a thousande thrée hundred &amp; twoe next insuing, that memorable &amp; bloudie battel of <hi>Flanders</hi> was fought, which to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> french men principally mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistred occasion of many a lamentable Alas: for in that battel, the floure of the
<pb facs="tcp:176506:26"/> French armie (I meane the chiefest in place and countenaunce) &amp; the gemme of all their glorie went to wracke, suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering deth no lesse ignominiously then tyrannically. And after that, <hi>Rodulph</hi> the Emperour, making séege against <hi>Verona,</hi> susteined great losse of his best appointed souldiours the Switzers, whose bloud embrewed y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> blades of their enimies, their bodies lying vppon the grounde groueling and senselesse: and the Emperour himself fighting against <hi>Albert</hi> duke of <hi>Austria</hi> was slaine, only Emperour elected but not crowned.<note place="margin">A Blasing star shooting vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, what afterwards insued.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now, what manifold miseries and mischiefes, a Blasing starre which shoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vpward, the head hanging downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, doth betoken, may soone be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued and knowne by the experience of a Blasing starre, which appeared in the West, &amp; tooke his course towarde the North, whiche starre was séene in the yeare of our Lord a thousand thrée hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thrée score and thrée. The woes wherof this starr gaue foreknowledge, fell vppon the Frenchemen, to their no small smart &amp; lamentable vnluckines:</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176506:27"/>
            <p>For in a foughten field against the Turkes, howebeit, out of the compasse of the French dominion, they were dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfited and ouerthrowen, a hundred thousand of them slaine with the sword, among which number was the Duke of Burgundie, who with the rest, lost his life without recouerie.</p>
            <p>Not long after which infortunate conflict, namely in the yere of our Lord 1406. Lodouicke Duke of Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and brother to the French king, was murthered at Parise moste traite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rously, and fraudulently: the losse of whose life, was death and destruction to a great number.</p>
            <p>And (that I may growe to an ende) who doeth not remember,<note place="margin">Strang things which haue followed after the appearing of a Blasing starre.</note> what grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous calamities did followe the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of a Blasing starr, in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> yere of our Lorde a thousand foure hundred thrée score and twelue, in the Moneth of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuarie, ouer Colen, Eastward, to the terrour of the beholders, and astonish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the hearers? There followed herevppon, in the Summer nexte and immediately insuing, a meruellous
<pb facs="tcp:176506:27"/> heate, ingendered euerie where in the earth, which was of such strength and vehemencie, that in some places, the fire brust out, and cast vp with it, euen the verie sand and grauell. Herevppon followed, not héere and there, but euery where, battels and murthers, mortall maladies, loathsome sickenesses, moste noysome and infectious: yea, so horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that I want wit, eyther in writing to leaue them witnessed, or by vterance to make them manifest. At whiche time also, the right renowmed Charles Duke of Burgundie, passed many warrelike aduentures, and atchieued manie a Martiall exploite, to his no small commendation and increase of deserued praise, notwithstanding the successe of battell is doubtfull and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous.</p>
            <p>In the yeare of our Lorde,<note place="margin">Further mis<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chiefes which haue followed after Blasing starres.</note> a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand foure hundred and eight, there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared a Blasing starre, which as in sight it was wonderfull and terrible, so it betokened mischiefes no lesse innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable, then eyther to heare, sée, or recount is moste lamentable: For not
<pb facs="tcp:176506:28"/> many dayes after, Luyck fel, &amp; certeine men to the number of 40.<note place="margin">Leege.</note> were cruelly slain. About that time also, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
               <hi>Prussians,</hi> entring battell against the king of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land were foyled, &amp; a slaughter, the like not heard of, made of them in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> conflict. At the same time also was the Counsel holden at <hi>Pisa</hi> dissolued &amp; ceassed, by a schisme most damnable: the cause of their conuocation &amp; meeting being for the making and confirming of vnitie.</p>
            <p>Therabout also beganne the Church to be yll appaid, and to stande in hazard of hauocke: whose present assistent <hi>Sigismund</hi> the king of Hungarie shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him selfe to be: in such sort with val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liauncie of spirit, that he might meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriously chalenge to be syrnamed, The most Christian king. Thus farre touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the euills, yea the heapes of euilles whiche Blasing stars haue portended, obserued by experience and triall to be true, by the euent and falling out of many misfortunes, whiche both long agoe,<note place="margin">The conclusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Chapter.</note> and also of late haue happened. It remaineth, that we knowe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be not foretokens also of some good,
<pb facs="tcp:176506:28"/> whiche although many vtterly deny, Yet neuerthelesse reade our further iudgement.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <head>Whether Blasing starres, doe not aswel betoken good, as yll. Chap. 12.</head>
            <p>HAuing before declared, by reasons not a few, and proued also by exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of veritie &amp; trueth, that Blasing starres for the most part are presigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant shewes and tokens of some mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe and euill: my thinkes I heare one asking me this question, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Blasing starres are not tokens of good, as they are signes of euill. To whom I make this resolution. First,<note place="margin">Blasing stars supernaturall signes sent from God.</note> so farre foorth as Blasing starres be su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall, there séemeth in this matter to reste no doubte: bicause al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, in the vnsearchable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>funditie of his wisedome, is wont by the appearing of starres, to giue signes to his beloued seruauntes, whom no doubt he hath foreelected to saluation, well of ioyfull newes as also of heauie tydinges.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176506:29"/>
            <p>For, hath hee not by the riseing of the Rainebowe in the cloudes of heauen,<note place="margin">The Rainbow a perpetuall assurance of Gods faithfull promise.</note> sealed securitie &amp; want of feare to the worlde, from beeing drowned, as some times it was in the dayes of our great auncientes? Did hee not by the retro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession &amp; backward going of the Sunne contrarie to the order of his course, sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie vnto <hi>Ezechias,</hi> that his life should be prolonged, &amp; that the number of his dayes were augmented? Did hee not also signifie vnto all nations, that the light was come into the worlde, which should shine in darknesse, namely Iesus Christ to bee borne for the saluation of all people: which thing he woulde haue testified by the appearing of a newe Orientall starre, visible to the eyes of the wise men, &amp; gloriously glistering? Euen so doubtelesse, there is no cause, why y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sight of a Blasing star should not breede in vs, as well hope of some good, as feare of some yll, according to the place and time where and when it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, since it is saide: <hi>Feare not the signes of Heauen, which the Gentiles feare: beecause the lawes of the people
<pb facs="tcp:176506:29"/> are vaine.</hi> Why then shoulde we stande in feare of those things, which haue not in them power, either to doe good or harme? Againe,<note place="margin">Blasing starres naturall may betoken some good.</note> so farre foorth as Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing starres are naturall, it is not to be douted, but that the appearing of them may portend and foreshewe some good: which is no hard or intricate matter to declare, as well by reason as also by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample. For, in so much as Blasing starres are made of fiue Planets (as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bienus</hi> affirmeth) namely of <hi>Venus, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter, Mars, Saturne,</hi> and <hi>Mercurie:</hi> and that those Blasing starrs which are made of <hi>Venus</hi> and <hi>Iupiter</hi> are princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally the best and luckiest, it cannot o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise be, but that Blasing starres, those specially whiche haue their influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence from <hi>Venus</hi> and <hi>Iupiter,</hi> shoulde sometimes betoken good, and not euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more yll. An example of good credit may that Blasing starre be, which when it appeared, was iudged so happie &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate to the Emperour <hi>Caesar Augus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> that then it was begunne to bee worshipped in the temple at <hi>Rome,</hi> and no where else throughout the whole
<pb facs="tcp:176506:30"/> world: because the Emperour beegin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning those shewes and pageants trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant, was by the appearing of that starre of seuen dayes continuance in the region of heauen, putt in hope and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation before hand of exceding great felicitie and happinesse to insue: which vndoubtedly he obteined in such sorte and manner, that none in regiment was counted happier then happie <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustus,</hi> as none was named better then the good <hi>Traianus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreouer, vppon the appearing of that starre,<note place="margin">The vanitie or superstition of the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant people &amp; grossehed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed multitude.</note> there bredde in the mindes of the Cōmonaltie an opinion of great reuerence, to witt, that by the Blasing starre was signified, the soule of <hi>Caesar</hi> to be receiued to immortalitie, and to enioy among the Gods aboundance of blessednesse: then which signification, they beléeued nothing more ioyfull or comfortable. So that we sée both by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and example, that their coniecture and opinion doeth not always deserue beléefe, which say, that Blasing starres neuer appeare, but therafter followeth some mischiefe and yl. Touching which
<pb facs="tcp:176506:30"/> matter, more might be saide to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of comfort, and the driuing away of despaire from the harts of the people, then we are disposed at this time to cal to memorie.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <head>To what countries and to what persons Blasing starres do principally beetoken yll. Chap. 13.</head>
            <p>THe question is asked, To what coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and to what people specially, Blasing starrs threaten mischiefe. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which demaunde doubtlesse, I might thinke no certeine aunswere can bee made: because all Blasing starres are not alike, eyther haue their generation from one and the selfe same cause: but some of them are naturall, othersome supernaturall, &amp; procéeding from God in the height of the heauens.</p>
            <p>Againe,<note place="margin">Blasing stars are vniuersal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed both on sea and land.</note> they are without difference so doubtfull in their significations, that <hi>Lucanus</hi> supposeth their influence to be so generall, that the beholders of them, eyther on Sea or Land, cannot assure them selues of safetie: and therefore they are vniuersally to be feared.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176506:31"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:176506:31"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:176506:32"/>
            <p>Vnto whose opinion I willingly as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, when Blasing starres supernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and procéeding from God doe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare. For this is of a certeintie, that it is Gods will, by them to betoken and threaten some yll, to all persons in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, which hauing offended and done wickedly against the prescript of his holie lawe, withdrawe not them selues from that puddle of pollusion and filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, wherein they wallowe, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue a life laden &amp; ouercharged with all manner of mischefe: whom he of his singular compassion and clemencie, would reuoke from their sinfulnesse, by the vision and sight of Blasing starres, as it were by horrible threateninges &amp; revokements, that by refourming their abhominable liues, they might frame their conuersation acceptable in his sight, according to his vnspeakable bountifulnesse, long suffering, &amp; pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, who still looketh for repentance be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore he taketh vengeance. As may ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifestly be gathered, by his dealing w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the <hi>Hierosolimites,</hi> whom he admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed of their wickednes, by a most hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible
<pb facs="tcp:176506:32"/> Blasing starr of a whole yeres ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing, daily looking when they would be warned, &amp; well appoynted with pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitence to preuent Gods sharp punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>But touching naturall Blasing star<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res,<note place="margin">Blasing starres naturall ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peare at Gods appointment.</note> Philosophers &amp; Astronomers haue otherwise iudged: howebeit, neither they shall at any time appeare without the singular sufferance of God, or some notable cause worthie remembrance. For my selfe thus I say, that as I am not of beléefe that they betoken &amp; proue in working as y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Astrologians dreame: So I do not vtterly condemne such as holde it much materiall and greatly to be regarded, towarde what parte of the worlde they shoote &amp; cast their beames, from what starres they drawe their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluencies and force, in what similitude and likenesse they appeare, what colour they carrie, at what season of the yeare they shewe, in what place, vnder what celestiall signes, and vnder what Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets aspect. For some there are, which holde this opinion, though groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vppon no kinde of reason, that
<pb facs="tcp:176506:33"/> a Blasing starre, bearing the likenesse of a Lute, Harpe, or semblable instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, betokeneth somwhat to Musicke and minstrelsie, and to the followers of such vanities. So likewise, when they carrie this representation or that, to haue in their likenesses semblant signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications.</p>
            <p>Againe, other are of this iudgment, that such blasing starrs as appeare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Saturne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The colour of Blasing starrs appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnder Planets.</note> are of a leaden colour: vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Iupiter,</hi> white: vnder <hi>Mars,</hi> redde: vnder <hi>Sol,</hi> Golden: vnder <hi>Mercurie,</hi> light azure: wherevppon it is thought no hard matter, to tell what they signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie in nature generally: Howbeit, to persons placed in dignitie, as to Popes, Cardinalles, Bishoppes, Emperours, Kings, Dukes, and suche like as are of place &amp; countenaunce in the Common wealth,<note place="margin">The modestie and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spection of the authour.</note> they foreshewe some euill: wherin as I holde it reuerence to be si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent: so were it ouermuch boldnesse &amp; presumption to be medling. What therefore may bee saide in this point, let Astronomers shewe their cunning.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:176506:33"/>
            <head>How and what way blasing starres are forewarnings of somewhat to come, and of force so to doe. Chap. 14.</head>
            <p>ALthough it may séeme diuersely and many wayes probable, that blasing starres foreshewe somewhat to insue: yet notwithstanding it is not necessarie that we should beléeue (as the Astrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians rashely holde opinion) that they can be signes or tokens of that thing, whereof they are no cause. For a Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing starre cannot be eyther the cause, or the effect of warre or death, albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it, it prognosticate &amp; foreshewe as a sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne from a naturall cause, both the one &amp; the other.</p>
            <p>It may bee (I will not denie) the cause after a sort:<note place="margin">Blasing stars are after a sort the cause of warr. pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. &amp;c.</note> as if that which is the cause of warre and Pestilence, we suppose also to bée the cause of the Blasing starre.</p>
            <p>As when aboundaunce of vapoures are drawen vpp into the aire, whiche being kindeled and sett on fire, there followeth and insueth the generation of a Blasing starre, &amp; infection of the
<pb facs="tcp:176506:34"/> aire, whiche bréedeth plague and pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, mouing mens mindes to muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, through the increase and plentie of choler stirred vpp in them: whereby they runne with main force to harnesse and weapon, and so to battell &amp; bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, not féeling in them any rule of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son restraining them in this their rash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse. Héerevpon (as it is not vnlike) spring commotions in kingdomes, and mutations of Common wealthes, then destruction: for, <hi>A realme diuided with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it selfe, beeing vnable long to laste, must needes come to losse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Blasing starres foretokens barrennesse.</note>Furthermore, séeing that the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of a naturall Blasing starre, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth that in some place hath béene great heate and drought, (for other wise such store of matter as is required to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ingendering thereof, could not be drawen vp:) it is woont to come to passe, that Blasing starres doe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly threaten barrennesse to Sandie and not to Fennie countries.</p>
            <p>Now, because it is likewise knowen, that by the force of starres, many enue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomed and infectious vapours ascend,
<pb facs="tcp:176506:34"/> it séemeth credible that a Blasing starr is a forewarning of a following pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,<note place="margin">Blasing stars foretokens of pestilence and mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</note> ingendered through the aire bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing choked and poysoned by vapours of suche qualitie. By whiche meanes in like maner, drougth setteth mens hearts on fire, and driueth them for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde to fall at strife, bralling, battell and bloudshed, it troubleth the braine, estrangeth the senses, and thus arise se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions. To conclude with the purpose, it is not greatly necessarie in this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, to vse longer delay, since I am of this beléefe, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> God of the aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunce of his loue towards vs, which is vnmesurable, by nature as a meane or méete instrumente, causeth suche and such Blasing starres to appeare: to the intent that he might by them as by premonishments and forewarninges, put vs in mind to remember, that it is time to start from sinne, &amp; to prepare our heartes with repentaunce, for the preuenting of those sharpe and smart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whips of Gods vengeaunce, which by suche Blasing starres, at Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, are threatened. For he
<pb facs="tcp:176506:35"/> neuer, or very seldome, since the creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the world plagued any people, but he sent among them some signe thereof, for their preparation to penitence, as in holie scriptures it is at large decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ Why blasing starres doe specially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>token yll to Peeres, Potentates, Rulers of realmes and commonwealthes. &amp;c Chap. 15.</head>
            <p>IT is the opinion of some, though er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronious, that Blasing stars doe spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially betoken yl to Princes and great men, and to their kingdomes also and Realmes threaten some mischiefe: in such wise, that it hath béene obserued &amp; marked, that no Blasing starre almoste hath appeared, but either death or else some yll hath hapened after, to some no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble personage in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> land: as by our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer examples it is left verified: which made <hi>Lucane</hi> the Poet to write of them, in this wise.</p>
            <q>
               <l>A Blasing starre in sight most straunge,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:176506:35"/>
               <l>The state of kingdomes, which doth change.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But it is héere demaunded, what the cause should bée,<note place="margin">Why Blasing starres beeto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken yll to peeres and po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tentates &amp;c.</note> that Blasing starres doe specially betoken yll to Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, Kinges, and such like noble per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonages? I answere, that there is none other cause, as they suppose, so farre foorthe as Blasing starres bée naturall, then because suche great estates and Péeres of Realmes, liuing more deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cately and vntemperately then other, are sooner subiecte and surprised with corrupt and empoysoned aire: and so they carrying close within them, and secretly nourishing the cause of yll in them selues, béeing vnpatient and not able to indure the working of medici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable receiptes, quickly perish and mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carrie.</p>
            <p>But so farre foorth as Blasing starrs are supernaturall,<note place="margin">Blasing starrs supernaturall are immediat forewarnings from God.</note> and as they haue their procéeding and béeing from the omnipotent GOD, it is thought this to be the cause: namely, that GOD is preparing a plage against them, that the blacke tentes of his indignation are
<pb facs="tcp:176506:36"/> a pitching, that the weapons of his vengeaunce are whetted against them, whereof he giueth forewarnings, like a most mercifull father: to the end they might vnderstand, that the cause of this Gods iust dealing, (being sinne and wickednes,) is either in Princes them selues, or else in the people vnder their vngratious gouernement: in conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration whereof, as well Prince as peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple might sée the horrour and abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of their owne sinnefull liues, and flée to repentance, whervnto God so fatherly would winne them by fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wareninges: that according to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of that holie King, they might lift vp both hearts and handes to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, saying. <hi>Enough nowe Lord, stay thy hande. It is I that haue offended: it is I that haue don wickedly: as for these innocent sheepe, what harme haue they done?</hi>
               <note place="margin">The wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of the people is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to the prince.</note> Furthermore, to whome doth a Blasing starre betoken somewhat to followe if not to the King? For in that it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> somewhat to the realme, it must ext<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d euen is the person of the King, who hath y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> rule &amp; gouernment of
<pb facs="tcp:176506:36"/> that realme: bicause he is a king, by his kingdom, &amp; bicause the wickednesse of the kingdome, is reputed the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ednesse of the king, who either by his insample giueth occasion of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse: or else hauing power and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to suppresse sinne in the people, neglecteth notwithstanding y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> due exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution and administration of iustice: so that the saying of the Apostle is most certeine &amp; vndoubted, that: All those whom God hath placed in authoritie,<note place="margin">A heauie rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning, for such as are in authoritie &amp; office.</note> and giuen préeminence vnto, are tyed to the necessitie of this heauie recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, not onely to stande accountable to almightie God for their owne, but also for the soules of all such ouer whom they haue charge. And therefore right aptly spake that moste wise and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie king <hi>Dauid</hi> to all kinges, (and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their title, to all suche as excell o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in office and dignitie:) <hi>And nowe ye kinges</hi> (saieth he) <hi>vnderstande, bee ye learned which iudge the earth, serue the Lord with feare, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus farre touching this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, whiche though it be but bluntly
<pb facs="tcp:176506:37"/> and shortly deliuered, yet is it to be marked.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ Of a certeine Blasing star which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in the yeare of our Lord, a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sande fiue hundred thirtie one, the nin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of Septemb. at Mentz, a citie in Germanie, and was sensibly seene like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise in other places. Chap. 16.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> question is asked, what that Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing starre, which was séene in the yeare of our Lord, 1531. might signifie, and to whome it is a foretoken of some euill to insue? In aunswering where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, I would to God I might not tell the truth so directly, as I did of an earth quake 3. yeares past, the effects where, of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> citie of <hi>Mentz,</hi> not without trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling tasted.<note place="margin">A Blasing starre betoke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geaunce from God.</note> The Blasing starre there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore which appeared An. 1531. betokenes a heauie burthen of vengeaunce, not onely to the state temporal, but also ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiasticall: yea it threateneth a plague to the whole worlde. The fashion and likenesse thereof signifieth no lesse, for it was to sée to, in forme of a broome, or a bundell of rodds. Which figure of a
<pb facs="tcp:176506:37"/> rodde, we doubte, forewarneth vs of that rodde, whereof the Lorde speaketh by the Prophet: <hi>I wil visite their iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties with the rodde, and their sinnes with stripes.</hi> For Almightie God vseth for more certeintie of forewarning, to giue vnto signes and tokens, the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses of things signified and betoke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. As for example.</p>
            <p>At what time his will was to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warne the Iewes of the Babylonicall captiuitie or bondage,<note place="margin">Forewarnings by signes bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring sēblance of things sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified.</note> hee spake thus to <hi>Ieremie</hi> y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Prophet: <hi>Make thee fetters &amp; chayns, &amp; put them about thy necke, &amp;c.</hi> Therby to signifie their captiuitie. So the same God, gaue a signe in the aire, of <hi>Titus</hi> &amp; <hi>Vespasianus</hi> his huge hoast against <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> to lay it waste: armed men with speares and launces running to and fro in warrelike wise which though they sawe manifestly, yet ceast they not to liue as they were wont, most wickedly: the vengeaunce of God falling vppon them,<note place="margin">A strāge sight and wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful a forewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of a blo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> battel.</note> which by those forewarnings was prophesied.</p>
            <p>In the yeare of our Lorde a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sande fiue hundred, there were seene
<pb facs="tcp:176506:38"/> falling from Heauen vpon mens gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, crosses, and there appeared in sensible maner, as certeine signs what shoulde after come to passe: namely, that bloudie battell betwéene the two worthy Princes, Rupert the thirde sonne of Philip, Palsegraue of Rhene and prince Electour: &amp; the noble prince Albert duke of <hi>Bauaria:</hi> the ensignes of the one hauing black crosses, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther redd: so that in the yeare a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand fiue hundred &amp; foure was fulfilled that, which in the yeare a thousand fiue hundred was foretolde.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, it is to bee feared, least the Blasing starre, which was séene in the likenesse of a rodde, threaten vnto vs that rodde, which the Prophet spake of, wherewith God is purposed in ius<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice to visite the wickednesse of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. For, if this Blasing starre be natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, wee shall perceiue nothing in it, which betokeneth not some greate euil. First,<note place="margin">All mischiefe commeth from the North.</note> because it blased so éeuen from the West to the North, from whence (as witnesseth the Prophet) all mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe doeth procéede, hauing neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse
<pb facs="tcp:176506:38"/> an aspect into other quarters of the worlde, terrible and threatening e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough.</p>
            <p>It was variable in colour, somtimes pale, that is Leaden and Saturnine, sometimes redde and Martiall. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, in so much as it continued (by the auerrement of Astronomers) vnder <hi>Saturne</hi> and <hi>Mars,</hi> Planets and signes of vnluckie influence, it séemeth to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>token not onely vnto one or two coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, but to the whole worlde, famine, warre, and pestilence: for it blased most terribly into all partes of the worlde.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, if the same Blasing starre were supernaturall, and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate from God, contrarie to the course &amp; order of Nature, it might not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise be thought, but that it betokened to the worlde much miserie &amp; woe: for God thereby signified, that his venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce was to come vppon all wicked worldlings, and vpon all such persons, as to their impenitence ioyne continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in sinne.</p>
            <p>Nowe, who hath the face to say a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
<pb facs="tcp:176506:39"/> this,<note place="margin">The horrible sin &amp; wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of the world prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth God to plague and punish with sharpnesse.</note> that the worlde hath taken such a surfette in iniquitie, &amp; is become so dronken in all abhomination, that Gods mercie is changed into iudgment and his patience into punishment, his loue into wrath, and his kindnesse in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to furie? In suche wise, that it may be supposed, God to speake vnto vs by this Blasing starr, as it were out of a cloud, in this maner:<note place="margin">A supposed speache of God expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing his wrath conceiued for iniquitie.</note>
               <hi>(The end of all fleshe is beefore mee. The earth is filled full of their iniquitie, and I will sweepe them away from the face of the earth. For they haue all plaid the startbacks, they haue walked in the byways of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and are become vnprofitable: in so much that there is none that doeth good, no not one.)</hi> Which as none can denie, so I thinke none dares but thus confesse, that the Blasing starre séene in our <hi>Horizon,</hi> betokeneth a common calamitie, considering howe iniquitie doth abound in all places, &amp; that sinne is grown to a perfect maturitie &amp; ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse: which God of his mercie giue vs grace to amende, that wee féele not the heate of his consuming anger, whereof
<pb facs="tcp:176506:39"/> hee hath sent vs a forewarning.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ Whether suche euilles as Blasing starres betoken, may by any meanes ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be preuented or auoyded. Chap. 17.</head>
            <p>IT remaineth, (most puissaunt Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour) the premisses considered, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> your maiestie taking the king of Nini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie for an ensample, rise from your seat of royaltie, and putting on sackcloth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with vs your people, lift vp our hands and heartes to heauen, like most humble suters, saying with king <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nasses</hi> in effecte as followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O almightie Lorde and God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The meanes to preuent &amp; auoide the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils which Blasing starres foreshew, is to pray, repent and amend &amp;c.</note>
               <hi>whose workemanshippe is the whole worlde, the heauen and the earth, with all the beautie and blessings of the same, at the presence of whose power all thinges quake and tremble, whose indignation when it threatneth vengeance vnto sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, is vnsufferable: and whose promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of mercie are vnmeasurable: bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause thou arte euen the moste highe
<pb facs="tcp:176506:40"/> Lord ouer all the earth, full of patience, forbearaunce, pittie, and repentaunce o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the wickednesse of sinfull people: delaying the sharpenesse of thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, for their amendement, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraunce from punishment. Thou, ô Lord, hast promised according to thy bottomlesse bountie and goodnesse, a penitent Spirite, not to iust and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Abraham, Isaac, and Iacob, whiche haue not offended against thy Maiestie: but to those that are ouerwhelmed with the tempestuos tydes of their trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wee (ô Lorde) haue offended, and our fathers haue cōmitted sinne in thy sight: We haue defiled our selues in the puddle of iniquitie: and therefore wee bow before thee the knees of our hearts, beseeching thee to be gratious vnto vs, and to open thine eares to our prayers. We haue sinned (ô Lord) we haue sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, &amp; we acknowledge our misdeedes, humbly beseeching thee to forgiue vs our offences. O forgiue vs, and deliuer vs not ouer to destruction with our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquities: neyther lay thou vp in store
<pb facs="tcp:176506:40"/> vengeance against the day of iudgemēt. O reserue not for vs the whip of woe &amp; wretchednesse: but in mercie pardon our misdeedes, and let not the fire of thy furie and wrath waxe hot against vs, to consume vs in our iniquitie, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, who is so blunt of iudgment, and dull of vnderstanding, that séeth not this confession of offences, this repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce &amp; contrition of heart, this hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling and submitting our selues both in soule &amp; bodie vnder the mightie hand of the omnipotent God, will pacifie and assuage the fiercenesse of his furie, &amp; so spare vs in compassion, through vnfeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned repentaunce, that we perishe not as outcastes from his fauour?</p>
            <p>Why should we not haue this hope and confidence in God, considering,<note place="margin">God doeth not exclude the penitent from the throne of grace, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth them to his mercie.</note> that to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> penitent Niniuites he did not shutt the gates of his compassion, but séeing their conuersion and forsaking of sinne, with the denyall of themselues &amp; all goodnesse in them, he receiued them againe to mercie, from which by their sinnes they were before excluded.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, it is not needfull that
<pb facs="tcp:176506:41"/> we stand in feare of the celestial signes:<note place="margin">Blasing stars, nor other signes appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in the heauen, are hurtful to any without the permission of God.</note> because without God they haue no po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer at all to preuaile against any peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: but béeing his seruaunts are at his commaundement, from whome all star<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res and all creatures haue their office and ministerie. To conceiue terror and feare therefore at the appearing of a Blasing starre, as betokening some euil like to followe, it is extreame mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse: let vs rather tremble at his all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightinesse, and feare the consuming flames of his iustice, who is the creator and maker not only of Blasing starres, but also of the Sunne, Moone, and Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, yea of reasonable man.</p>
            <p>And let vs not thinke, but that God, who framed the whole worlde, the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen aboue, and the earth belowe, is able as he made them, so to rule them: for at his commaundement are all things within the compasse of the Heauen, bée they starres, or whatsoeuer else: so that he can, according to the greatnesse of his power, which filleth all places, chaunge and dispose them, after his owne plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure: yea the threatening tokens of his iudgment &amp; vengeaunce, will he turne
<pb facs="tcp:176506:41"/> into forberance and forgiuenesse,<note place="margin">To neglects the time of our visitation hasteneth Gods heauie and sharp pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment.</note> if we penitently neglect not (as did the Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es) the time of our visitation. For they béeing warned by many wonders, and among others, by a Blasing starr of no lesse horrour then continuaunce, lay slugging in the couche of securitie and carlessenesse: and not regarding the threates of God for sinne, either of wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full blindenesse, or stoute stubbernesse, coūted those tokens of Gods vnsuffera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble wrath, elementarie apparitions &amp; toyes méere contemptible.</p>
            <p>But let not vs suffer our selues to be lulled a sléepe in the cradle of sensu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alitie:<note place="margin">It is good to be warned by the example of others.</note> let vs not be droncken with the dregges of their abhomination: let not the vanities of our owne heartes so be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witch vs, that we fall into a selfe loue &amp; lyking of our owne selues, neglecting the profered time of grace and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing kindenesse, lest God deliuering vs ouer to reprobation in his vnappeasea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble displeasure, plague vs with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same rod of reuengment for our vngratious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, wherwith he tooke vengeance vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them for their wilfull stubbernesse.
<pb facs="tcp:176506:42"/> Which, that it may not come to passe, let vs in time turne to the Lorde, and in due seson take his fatherly admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as readie meanes to leade vs to repentance, &amp; the auoyding of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> scourge of destruction, wherewith he punisheth the impenitent. From the whiche deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs O Lorde God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To the Allmightie, Euerlasting, Inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible, and Onely wise GOD, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore All, aboue All, &amp; in All, be all Laude, Honour, Glorie, Dominion and Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie for euer &amp; euer. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:176506:42"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>